All right, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Good ערב יום כיפור. erev Yom
Kippur. We pick up on the משנה Mishna on ל"א ע"ב. Lamed-Aleph
Amud-Bet.
Thank you Michael in absentia for filling for me. That was not
necessarily an easy דף daf yesterday, working through the implications of the
position of בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, how it fits in the משנה
Mishna that הקדש בטעות hekdesh b'taut is הקדש. hekdesh. But this משנה
Mishna turns to נזירות בטעות Nezirot b'taut or both נזירות Nezirot and
הקדש בטעות, hekdesh b'taut, so it builds on the assumptions of the
previous משנה. Mishna. So let's take a look at the משנה Mishna
on the bottom of ל"א ע"ב. Lamed-Aleph Amud-Bet.
מי שנדר בנזיר. Mi shenadar b'Nazir. Oops, I forgot to start this.
Hold on. There we go. Boom. Let's go.
All right. מי שנדר בנזיר. Mi shenadar b'Nazir. So the משנה Mishna
on the bottom of ל"א ע"ב, Lamed-Aleph Amud-Bet, continuing in this discussion
of טעות. taut. מי שנדר בנזיר. Mi shenadar b'Nazir. Somebody took a
vow of נזירות. Nezirot. ונשאל לחכם, Venishal l'chacham, and he asked a
שאלה sheila for a חכם chacham to get a היתר. heter. ואסרו,
Ve'asaro, and the חכם chacham was not able to מתיר matir it
for him. He actually said, 'I'm sorry, buddy, you're stuck.' Okay, now,
I'll just mention parenthetically that since we are going to say in
a later משנה, Mishna, we haven't said it explicitly, I mean the
גמרא Gemara said it, but anyway, that בית שמאי Beit Shammai holds
that even נזירות בטעות Nezirot b'taut is נזירות, Nezirot, תוספות Tosfot says
that for this משנה Mishna to work according to בית שמאי, Beit
Shammai, it must be what he asked the חכם chacham was not
some type of a sense of a normal היתר heter or a
פתח petach for a נדר, neder, which would not work for בית
שמאי Beit Shammai for נזירות, Nezirot, but what he basically said was,
'Well, maybe the language wasn't a legitimate language.' You know, the whole
מסכת masechet began נזיר,
נזיק, נזיח, פזיח, Nazir, Nazik, Naziach, Paziyach, etc. So there are sometimes
ways you say it which it wasn't just, 'Yes, I said the
right words, but had I thought it through, I wouldn't have accepted
it.' That would be a type of a טעות taut or a
פתח petach case. This could be a case where you're actually asking
a חכם chacham to say, 'Maybe I didn't say the right formula,'
and get, you know, get off the hook because of that. So
that just covers situations that even בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say
it's possible that you would get out of your, you could get
out of your נזירות Nezirot if you didn't say the right formula.
But one way or another way, you're going to a חכם, chacham,
either you think you might not have said the right formula, or
according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, you were a bit, it was
a טעות taut or you regret it, some type of a reason
you think that it, you know, had you been thinking it through,
you wouldn't have accepted it, and the חכם chacham said, 'I'm sorry,
I can't help you, and you're stuck with your נזירות.' Nezirot. So,
מונה משעה שנדר. monei mishaa shenadar. Fine, you do your נזירות Nezirot
from the time you accepted your נדר. neder. Now, that's pretty obvious.
I mean, what's it saying? Of course you do. So the גמרא
Gemara is going to assume that the חידוש chiddush here is
even if you violated your נזירות. Nezirot. Let's say the reason you
went to the חכם chacham was you, I don't know, you forgot
and you drank wine, or you did something. You violated your נזירות
Nezirot and then you really need to go to the חכם chacham
to get it undone retroactively. Very appropriate for יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
Let's see if we can get all of our עבירות aveirot retroactively
undone because we have חרטה. charata. Okay, so that's basically what this
is. Okay, you had your חרטה, charata, but unfortunately here the חכם,
chacham, maybe God is more compassionate, but the חכם chacham said you're
stuck with it. Now, so the חידוש chiddush is, is the משנה
Mishna saying that even though you violated, when you're טמא, tamei, then
the תורה Torah says, you know, you bring a קרבן, korban, you
start over again. But let's say you violated in other ways. You
drink wine, you shave and so on, you cut your hair. So
there actually, according to the תורה, Torah, you don't start your נזירות
Nezirot over. You violated, you get punished for your violations, right, if
you're warned you get lashes and so on. But the amount, but
your duration is the same. Okay, it goes from the time you
accepted your נזירות. Nezirot. You don't have to do any extra days.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to assume to be
the case in the משנה, Mishna, although the, you know, a key
factor that you violated your נזירות Nezirot is not written here, but
that's what it's going to assume is the point. So then it
says the next, the next line. נשאל לחכם והתירו. Nishal l'chacham vehitiro.
Now let's say the חכם chacham was מתיר matir your נדר neder
or according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai said you didn't even do
the right formula and therefore you're not a נזיר. Nazir. היתה לו
בהמה מופרשת. Hayta lo behema mufreshet.
And you had an animal that you had already sanctified. תצא ותרעה
בעדר. Tetzei v'tir'eh ba'eder.
So retroactively it's not sanctified
because it's, you were never נזיר Nazir and therefore as תוספות Tosfot
says, it's like you sanctified an animal as a חטאת chatat and
you didn't have a sin that you needed to bring the חטאת
chatat for. So you just don't have the right context. Forget, you
know, if you're not a נזיר, Nazir, you can't sanctify an animal
as a קרבן korban of a נזירות. Nezirot. So retroactively the animal
is not sanctified at all. So אמרו בית הלל לבית שמאי. amru
Beit Hillel l'Beit Shammai.
So בית הלל Beit Hillel said to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, so
this presumably was a משנה Mishna that was an earlier משנה. Mishna.
It's always very fascinating when בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי
Beit Shammai refer to an earlier משנה, Mishna, which basically shows the
history of the development of the משנה. Mishna. The גמרא Gemara sometimes
talks about a concept called, or not the גמרא, Gemara, the משנה
Mishna sometimes talk about a concept of משנה ראשונה, Mishna Rishona, the
first משנה. Mishna. So for example, the very beginning of פסחים, Pesachim,
right, the first משנה Mishna in פסחים Pesachim says, כל מקום שאין
מכניסין בו חמץ אין צריך בדיקה. kol makom she'ein machnisin bo chametz
ein tzarich bdika. Wherever you don't bring חמץ, chametz, you don't have
to check. שתי שורות במרתף. Shetei shurot b'martef. So what's the teaching
of the two rows of the wine cellar? So בית הלל Beit
Hillel says it means these two rows and בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says it means those two rows. So whoever said anything about two
rows of a wine cellar? What it shows you is that there
was... Later tonight I'm in בית הלל Beis Hillel בית שמאי Beis
Shammai and not even so late are debating an earlier משנה Mishna
which was a universally accepted משנה. Mishna. So you have the same
point here. Apparently the משנה Mishna we just quoted
was early and accepted by everyone. And now בית הלל Beis Hillel
is going to use this משנה Mishna to make an argument against
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. So let's take a look. So אמרו בית
הלל לבית שמאי, amru Beis Hillel l'Beis Shammai, אי אתם מודים בזה
שהוא הקדש טעות, ee atem modim b'ze she'hu hekdesh taut,
look we teach that if a guy retroactively wasn't a נזיר Nazir
because he got a היתר heter from a חכם chacham that the
animal is not קדוש. kadosh. So that seems to be a case
of הקדש טעות, hekdesh taut, something that was sanctified which was now
retroactively we see in error and what do you see the הלכה
halacha is? You see that a הקדש טעות hekdesh taut is not
הקדש. hekdesh. This early משנה Mishna teaches that the animal is not
קדוש. kadosh. אי אתם מודים בזה שהוא הקדש טעות שתצא ותרעה בעדר
ee atem modim b'ze she'hu hekdesh taut sheteitzei v'tir'eh b'eder and it
goes out and it grazes in the flock. So how could you
say הקדש טעות hekdesh taut is הקדש? hekdesh? This משנה Mishna teaches
you that if the guy turns out retroactively to have not have
been a נזיר, Nazir, it's not the קרבן korban isn't sanctified. So
אמרו להן בית שמאי, amru lahen Beis Shammai, so בית שמאי Beis
Shammai said back to them, I'll give you a counter-example. אי אתם
מודים במי שטעה וקרא לתשיעי עשירי ולעשירי תשיעי ולאחד עשר עשירי שהוא
מקודש, ee atem modim b'mi she'tah v'kara l'tshi'i asiri v'la'asiri tshi'i v'la'achad
asar asiri shehu mukdash,
when you're taking מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behema, okay,
again I guess I'm thinking about יום כיפור Yom Kippur because it's
a day away like כבקרת רועה עדרו מעביר צאונו תחת שבטו. k'vakarat
ro'eh edro ma'avir tzono tachat shivto.
That's the story about מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behema. You got all your
new animals that were born that year, you put them in a
pen, they walk out from one door and you count them one,
two, three with your staff and the tenth one you hit, actually
you got some like red dye on your staff so you mark
it and that one is מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behema. Now let's say
you accidentally miscounted and you count when number nine walked out you
said ten or when number eleven walked out you said ten. So
the הלכה halacha there is that they're also מעשר. ma'aser. So בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says look here's an example where הקדש טעות hekdesh
taut is הקדש. hekdesh. You said ten on nine and it's still
הקדש. hekdesh. So don't you admit אי אתם מודים במי שטעה וקרא
לתשיעי עשירי ee atem modim b'mi she'tah v'kara l'tshi'i asiri if you
call nine ten or עשירי תשיעי asiri tshi'i and accidentally ten nine
or אחד עשר עשירי achad asar asiri and you call eleven ten,
so you went you did ten, oops, nine, oops, ten, or whatever
anyway so in that case שהוא מקודש shehu mukdash all three of
them are קדוש kadosh apparently, number ten because it was ten and
number nine and eleven because you called them ten. Anyway so you
see הקדש טעות hekdesh taut is הקדש. hekdesh. אמרו להן בית הלל,
amru lahen Beis Hillel, so בית הלל Beis Hillel said back to
them לא השבט קידשה, lo hashevet kidshah,
no it is not the staff that made them קדוש, kadosh, it
is not the fact that anything that you touch with your staff
and say ten is הקדש hekdesh because of הקדש טעות, hekdesh taut,
that's not the way the mechanism worked. ומה אי אלו טעה והניח
את השבט על שמיני ועל שנים עשר, uma ee ilu ta'ah v'hini'ach
et hashevet al shmini v'al shneim asar, I'll prove to you that
that's the truth.
Let's say number eight you accidentally call ten or number twelve you
accidentally call ten. שמא עשה כלום shema asa klum do you think
that that works? Of course it doesn't. It's only a הלכה halacha
of nine and eleven. So what does that mean? Why is it
only a הלכה halacha about nine and eleven? אלא כתוב שקידש עשירי
הוא קידש תשיעי ואת אחד עשר. ela katuv shekidesh asiri hu kidesh
tshi'i v'et achad asar.
This is not a הלכה halacha that you instill קדושה kedusha to
the animal. The תורה Torah says the tenth one is מעשר. ma'aser.
Okay how do you designate how do you identify the tenth one?
It's the tenth one that walks out you call it ten so
we're going to learn from a פסוק pasuk that if you're off
by one that's like within a margin of error that's considered like
within ten plus or minus one. So it's like it's within the
category of מעשר ma'aser but the reason that works is not because
you just instilled a קדושה. kedusha. If you took a random animal
and you said this is מעשר ma'aser and it was really number
eight you would not instill the קדושה kedusha so it's not an
issue of הקדש טעות, hekdesh taut, it's an issue about how the
תורה Torah designates what's considered ten. The תורה Torah says the tenth
one is the tenth one or the ninth or the eleventh if
you make a mistake and you call it ten that's also ten
but that's a special הלכה halacha in מעשר בהמה ma'aser behema that
that constitutes close enough to the tenth to be considered מעשר בהמה,
ma'aser behema, okay, but that's not a general הלכה halacha that if
you accidentally sanctify something it's הקדש hekdesh and the proof is that
even in מעשר בהמה ma'aser behema if you call the eighth one
ten it wouldn't be הקדש hekdesh so it's not that every error
automatically you're stuck with it it's within this parameter of מעשר בהמה.
ma'aser behema. So that's how בית הלל Beis Hillel responds to בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai. How does בית שמאי Beis Shammai respond to בית
הלל? Beis Hillel? So בית הלל Beis Hillel says look if it
turned out you weren't a נזיר Nazir this thing isn't קדוש kadosh
that shows הקדש טעות hekdesh taut doesn't work. So תוספות Tosafot says
that was such an obvious answer they didn't even have to respond
to בית הלל. Beis Hillel. Why is it obvious? Because that's not
הקדש טעות. hekdesh taut. There you're missing the basic criteria to enable
you to sanctify. If you're not a נזיר Nazir you can't sanctify
an animal as a קרבן נזירות. korban nezirut. If you're not obligated
in a חטאת chatat and you take an animal and you say
this will be for my for my חטאת chatat for eating חלב
chelev and you haven't eaten חלב, chelev, it's not קדוש. kadosh. You
don't have to say oh look הקדש טעות hekdesh taut doesn't work.
Okay yes there was a type of a טעות taut because you
thought you were obligated but that's not the reason it doesn't work.
It doesn't work because you don't have the basic criteria necessary for
sanctifying that type of an animal. You have to be obligated in
a חטאת chatas to make a חטאת. chatas. You have to be
a נזיר nazir to sanctify something as a קרבן נזירות. korban nezirus.
That's so obvious. Not obvious at all when you talk about הקדש.
hekdesh.
When he made,
when he set aside the animal,
he was a נזיר. nazir. So then later on retroactively you cancel
it? It's not so obvious that הקדש hekdesh is void.
Right, I mean what if you live in a world in which
we reassess things retroactively? You're right, I mean you could say בשעת
מעשה bishas ma'aseh you were, so it's still binding even if retroactively
not. But at least what you could
say
is
it's not relevant to תוספות. Tosafos. The תוספות Tosafos idea is I
have the power, but I said what I didn't intend to say.
Or I misidentified something or something of that nature.
Well, I mean תמורה temurah is like that, right? So the same
with תמורה. temurah.
Right, well according to one לימוד, limud, בית שמאי Beis Shammai gets
their idea from תמורה. temurah. But in all those cases
you didn't even ever have the power to make a to do
a תמורה, temurah, and yet it's a תמורה. temurah.
Well, no, I mean actually you do have the power. You're not
allowed to, you're not
empowered to. Right. Okay, but the point is is that here bottom
line is that you didn't satisfy the basic criteria. It's true only
retroactively you didn't satisfy the criteria, but anyway that's what תוספות, Tosafos,
if you want to look, you want to see if you believe
it more if תוספות Tosafos says it. תוספות Tosafos says like this,
he says, and
he says the תוספות נשאל Tosafos nishal about six lines from the
bottom, two lines above the א aleph in brackets. He says, or
three lines above, it says וכאן הנזירות ליתא הקדש נמי ליתא וגרוע
זה מהקדש טעות וכך אפילו בית שמאי מודו דתיבטל לאלתר vechan hanezirus
leisa hekdesh nami leisa vegarua zeh mehekdesh ta'us vechach afilu Beis Shammai
modu detivtal le'alter כיון דנעקר הנדר לגמרי keivan dene'ekar haneder legamrei retroactively
you weren't a נזיר nazir at all כדאמר לקרבנות
נזירות כגון kedamar lekorbanos nezirus kegon I don't know what that
אף af switches the גירסא girsa a little bit, כיון דאמר לקרבנות
נזירות נזי נזירותו לא אמר כלום keivan de'amar lekorbanos nezirus nezi neziruso
lo amar klum
since he said that this will be the קרבנות korbanos for my
נזירות, nezirut, נזי נזירותו, nezi neziruso, לא אמר כלום lo amar klum
דהוה כאדם שאינו מחוייב והיה סבור שהוא מחוייב חטאת ואמר בהמה זו
לחטאת לא אמר כלום אפילו לבית שמאי. dehaveh ke'adam she'eino mechuyav vehaya
savur shehu mechuyav chatas ve'amar behema zu lechatas lo amar klum afilu
leBeis Shammai.
Okay,
so yes, are you in an error? You are in an error
because you think you're a נזיר, nazir, you think you're obligated in
a חטאת. chatas. But the reason it didn't work wasn't because of
your error. The reason it didn't work was because you didn't have
the basic context and criteria to make that type of a הקדש.
hekdesh. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So
the first part that the גמרא Gemara focuses on is not the
הקדש טעות hekdesh ta'us but this first line which seems innocuous in
the משנה mishna that says the חכם chacham wasn't מתיר matir it
for you, you count from the day your נזירות nezirus began, which
is obvious. So the גמרא Gemara therefore assumes what it means is
even if you violated your נזירות, nezirus, not became טמא tamei but
violated like drank wine, you would still count from the day it
began. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, top of ל"ב. lamed
beis. מני מתניתין? mani masnisin? Who's our משנה? mishna? לא רבי יוסי
ולא רבנן lo Rebbi Yosei velo rabanan דתניא detanya מי שנדר ועבר
על נזירותו, mi shenadar ve'avar al neziruso, somebody made a vow, became
a נזיר nazir and then he violated it, he drank wine let's
say. אין נזקקין לו, ein nizkakin lo, you do not sort of
like take care of him, attend to him, meaning you don't accept
his קרבנות korbanos is the way it's to be understood, אלא אם
כן מונה בהן איסור כיומים שנהג בהן היתר. ela im kein moneh
bahen issur keyamim shenahag bahen hetter. Unless he first makes up all
the days that he violated. Now what does it mean? Meaning he
practices with prohibition, not drinking wine, like the days that he practiced
that it was permissible. So if he accepted a נזירות nezirus of
a hundred days and he drank wine for forty-five days, so he
comes to us on day forty-six, we'd have to say you have
to or whatever meaning before we're ready to accept his קרבנות, korbanos,
he'd have to do a full hundred days of not drinking wine.
He'd have to make up the days that he violated.
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosei says, דייו שלושים יום. dayo shloshim yom. No,
even in that case it's enough that he only makes up thirty
days, a full sort of unit of נזירות nezirus even if he
violated more than that. So the גמרא Gemara says, so either way
though you have to make up a certain amount of days that
you violated. And the משנה mishna says that you do from the
beginning of your נזירות. nezirus. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אי רבנן קשיא נזירות מועטת. ei rabanan kashya nezirus mu'etes. If it's
the רבנן, rabanan, so even a short נזירות nezirus is a problem
because you have to to make up the full amount of days
that you violated. And אי ee רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi and if
it's רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, קשיא נזירות מרובה. kashya Nezirus meruba. It's
difficult a long נזירות Nezirus because he would say you have to
do thirty days if you violated a lot. Now it's not clear
why it matters מועטת mu'etes or מרובה. meruba. You know bottom line,
bottom line, excuse me. Let me see real יצר הרע yeitzer hara
because it's יום כיפור Yom Kippur tonight so I can't drink too
much caffeine but I really need it this morning.
I don't know if it's a מצוה mitzvah to have caffeine. Anyway,
okay. All right so,
okay so it's not at all clear why this the גמרא Gemara
is assuming that this works better
for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi in the case of נזירות מועטת Nezirus
mu'etes because either way according to both approaches you have to make
up a certain amount of days that you violated.
But so one way or another the משנה Mishnah says you don't
have to. Let's see what the answer is and maybe we could
a little bit understand the difference of the גמרא Gemara between מועטת
mu'etes and מרובה. meruba. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אי
בעית אימא רבי יוסי ואי בעית אימא רבנן. ee ba'is eima Rabbi
Yossi ve-ee ba'is eima Rabbanan. I could make the משנה Mishnah work
either according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi or the רבנן. Rabbanan. אי
בעית אימא רבי יוסי, ee ba'is eima Rabbi Yossi, here's how it
could work according to רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. כאן בנזירות מרובה כאן
בנזירות מועטת. kan be-Nezirus meruba kan be-Nezirus mu'etes. So here the גמרא
Gemara does draw a line between מרובה meruba and מועטת. mu'etes. So
what does that mean? How to read that? So there are two
ways the ראשונים Rishonim read what this means. One is, and this
is like a pretty radical re-read of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, that
when רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says דיו שלשים יום, dayo shloshim yom,
it doesn't mean it's enough to make up thirty days if you
violated for forty-five days, you just make up thirty days. You know
how you could read דיו שלשים יום? dayo shloshim yom? דיו שלשים
יום dayo shloshim yom which is
look, you've been a נזיר nazir for thirty days. I don't care
how many days you violated. Meaning it could be that רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi is completely rejecting the idea that you have to make
up the days. It could be that the ברייתא braita is talking
about a נזירות מועטת Nezirus mu'etes and when רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
says the Rabbis say you have to make up the days you
violated and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says why not, why does he
have to? He did his thirty days, I don't care if he
violated דיו שלשים יום. dayo shloshim yom. So therefore if that's how
you read it, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi fundamentally disagrees there's a need
to make up the days. So therefore the ברייתא braita is נזירות
מועטת Nezirus mu'etes and when רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says thirty days
he just means thirty days from the onset. And that's when the
משנה Mishnah says you count from the onset, that's רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yossi. That could be talking about a big נזירות, Nezirus, right? And
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi basically is a way of saying that רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi says you never have to make up any days.
Okay, so that's a pretty radical, you know, re-read of that. The
other way of saying it is is the flip, is that when
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says thirty days, that's when it was a
long נזירות Nezirus and let's say you violated forty-five and he says
thirty is enough. Okay, but how do you explain the משנה? Mishnah?
The משנה Mishnah says that you count from the day that you
began, right? מי שנדר בנזיר mi-she-nadar be-nezir etc. you go from משעת
שנדר. mi-sha'at she-nadar. So the, so this read would say one of
two ways. Either, now this would also be strange, if it's a
short נזירות Nezirus and you only violated a small number of days
then רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi will be מוחל mochal making it up.
He only makes you make up thirty days when you violated a
lot, but if you violated a small amount maybe he doesn't make
you make them up, okay that's my explanation I didn't see anybody
say that. Or the other explanation that תוספות Tosafos says or the
ראש Rosh says is when it says מונה משעת שנדר moneh mi-sha'at
she-nadar it means that like, you know, you don't have to do
it all over again. Like somehow מונה משעת שנדר moneh mi-sha'at she-nadar
means you most like, you know, some somehow again I'm having a
hard time explaining it because I don't really understand it. But somehow
מונה משעת שנדר moneh mi-sha'at she-nadar means like, you know, you you
count
mostly from the day that you began if you missed a few
days you'll make up those days but it's not like a fundamental
starting over again. Okay, so one way is to read it like
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi and to say that it is true you
have to make up the days that you missed but it's only
a few days and the משנה Mishnah maybe isn't really focusing on
that. Okay, אי בעית אימא ee ba'is eima and if you want
רבנן Rabbanan you could say it's the Rabbis and לא תימא משעת
שנדר אלא אימא כמשעת שנדר, lo teima mi-sha'at she-nadar ela eima ke-mi-sha'at
she-nadar, a
very another radical re-read of the משנה. Mishnah. When the Rabbis say
מונה משעת moneh mi-sha'at when the משנה Mishnah says מונה משעת שנדר
moneh mi-sha'at she-nadar it does not mean that you count from the
day you began. If I took the נזירות Nezirus on January 1st
I count my thirty days from January 1st. It means I have
to recount
from the day that I began until today because those are all
the days that I violated. So if I took the vow on
January 1st and I've been drinking wine for 15 days and I
show up to the חכם chacham on January 15th, okay so now
he says sorry buddy I can't help you you're stuck you gotta
keep your נזירות. Nezirus. So מונה משעת שנדר moneh mi-sha'at she-nadar means
count my thirty days from January 1st. מונה כמשעת
שנדר moneh ke-mi-sha'at she-nadar means it's been 15 days since January 1st
I have to recount those 15 days because I've been violating for
the last 15 days I have to recount all the days that
I've been violating. Okay so by sticking in the כף chaf it
basically is telling me I have to recount those days since since
I've accepted the נזירות. Nezirus. Okay so again it's very strange. The
משנה Mishnah doesn't mention that I violated at all. The גמרא Gemara
doesn't even bother spelling it out, takes for granted that I've violated
or else why would the משנה Mishnah be telling it to me?
And then we've got the משנה Mishnah telling that even if I
violated I don't have to make up those days and here you
have a רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi or רבנן Rabbanan that say I
do have to make up those
days. So. Or to reread the משנה Mishnah to say that I
actually do have to make up those days that I missed. Okay,
let's now go on.
מי שהלך
לחכם והתירוהו. Mi she-halach la-chacham vehitiruhu. So that was actually a little
parenthetical because it wasn't even clear in the משנה, Mishnah, but now
we've read this משנה Mishnah to say that there's an idea of
making up days if I violate. But now we get to what
seems to be the focus of the משנה, Mishnah, which is the
issue about הקדש טעות hekdesh ta'os and בית הלל Beis Hillel and
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. So actually we went and I did get
the vow released, even if I had sanctified an animal as a
קרבן, korban, retroactively it's not a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר רבי ירמיה מדיבית שמאי נשמע לבית הלל. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah:
Mi-deBeis Shammai nishma leBeis Hillel. From בית שמאי Beis Shammai we can
infer according to בית הלל. Beis Hillel. למה מדיבית שמאי הקדש טעות
הוי הקדש. Lama? MiBeis Shammai, hekdesh ta'os havei hekdesh. בית שמאי Beis
Shammai says a הקדש hekdesh in error is a הקדש. hekdesh. And
nevertheless, even though they say that, כיון דאיגלאי מילתא דלאו שפיר נזר,
keivan de-iglei milta d'lav shapir nazar, once it turns out that you
weren't a נזיר nazir retroactively, so you were missing the basic criteria
for the הקדש hekdesh at all, it wasn't just טעות, ta'os, you
fundamentally weren't a נזיר, nazir, תאתי וירעה בעדר. tatei ve-yir'eh ba'eder. So
they would admit that the animal is not sanctified and can go
and graze in the flock. So even though they say הקדש בטעות
hekdesh be-ta'os is הקדש, hekdesh, if you fundamentally undermine the basic context,
the basic criteria, it wouldn't be הקדש hekdesh at all. If that's
true for בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, similarly for בית הלל. Beis Hillel.
ולבית הלל נמי אף על גב דאמר תמורה בטעות הוי תמורה. U-leBeis
Hillel nami af al gav d'amar temurah be-ta'os havei temurah. Even though
they say a תמורה temurah in error is a תמורה, temurah, הני
מילי היכא דאיכא עיקר הקדש. Hani milei heicha d'ika ikar hekdesh. That's
when the thing is קדוש, kadosh, the original animal, and you just
made some type of an error. Okay, so that's when they say
you're stuck with the error. Like בית שמאי Beis Shammai says in
general, בית הלל Beis Hillel says by תמורה. temurah. אבל היכא דאיתעקר
עיקר הקדש, Aval heicha d'itakar ikar hekdesh, but if the basic הקדש
hekdesh is fundamentally
undermined, איתעקר נמי תמורה, itakar nami temurah, the תמורה temurah would be
undermined. What would be the case? The animal that I had was
an עולה. olah. I said, זו תמורת זו, zu temuras zu, okay,
that would be a תמורה. temurah. Let's say, however, the original animal
that was an עולה, olah, I went to a חכם chacham and
I got a היתר heter on my original הקדש hekdesh of that
animal as an עולה. olah. Okay, or I don't know, let's say
it turned out that that animal didn't belong to me, some type
of a way that the original animal wasn't הקדש hekdesh to begin
with. Not because of a טעות, ta'os, but for some other reason,
I got a
היתר, heter, or even if it was a טעות, ta'os, the original
הקדש hekdesh is according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, טעות ta'os is
relevant. It's only not relevant for the תמורה, temurah, but it is
relevant for the original הקדש. hekdesh. So if the original הקדש hekdesh
wasn't in place, the תמורה temurah also doesn't work. Okay, you need
to start with a base and on that base you can build
the idea, oh it was a טעות, ta'os, you're stuck with your
טעות. ta'os. But there has to have been that base. So for
בית הלל Beis Hillel the original animal has to be הקדש hekdesh
in case of תמורה, temurah, and for בית שמאי Beis Shammai the
base is you have to be a נזיר. nazir. If you're not
a נזיר, nazir, you can't talk about being מקדיש בטעות, makdish be-ta'os,
קרבן korban of a נזיר. nazir. If you're not a נזיר, nazir,
you don't have the basic base to allow that act to take
place. All right, so that's pretty straightforward. Do you have a question,
Charlie?
No, it kicks on you'll probably answer.
All right, let's take a look now at the end of the
משנה. Mishnah. So that's בית שמאי Beis Shammai tried, בית הלל Beis
Hillel tried to prove their case from the guy that retroactively wasn't
a נזיר. nazir. בית שמאי Beis Shammai didn't even bother to respond.
That was clearly not just a טעות ta'os case, but a case
where the basic context, the basic criteria were lacking. And now we
go with בית שמאי Beis Shammai trying to prove it from מעשר.
ma'aser. Okay, and then בית הלל's Beis Hillel response, that's not טעות,
ta'os, that's just a תורת הלכה Toras halacha that nine and eleven
also count as ten. Okay, אתמר. itmar. So אמר מר, Amar Mar,
אי אתם מודים שאילו קרא לתשיעי עשירי. iy attem modim she-ilu kara
le-tishi asiri. אתמר itmar was taught. מעשר. ma'aser. רב נחמן אמר טעותו
ולא כוונתו, Rav Nachman amar: te'uso ve-lo kavanato, that when do we
say eleven and nine count as מעשר? ma'aser? If you accidentally called
eleven and nine ten. But if you intentionally, you knew it was
eleven and you called it ten, that would not be מעשר. ma'aser.
ורב חסדא ורבה בר בר חנה אמרי טעותו וכל שכן כוונתו. Ve-Rav
Chisda ve-Rabbah bar bar Chana amri: te'uso ve-chol she-ken kavanato. No, error
and certainly if you intentionally wanted to sanctify it as ten
knowing it was eleven, that would also give it a status of
ten. Okay, interesting. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן. Amar lei Rava le-Rav
Nachman. So רבא Rava said to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, לדידך דאמרת
טעותו ולא כוונתו, Le-didach d'amrat te'uso ve-lo kavanato, according to you that
you say it's only an error when nine and eleven get to
be counted as ten, דקאמרי בית שמאי לבית הלל, De-ka-amri Beis Shammai
leBeis Hillel, when בית שמאי Beis Shammai says to בית הלל, Beis
Hillel, אי אתם מודים שאילו קרא לתשיעי עשירי ולעשירי תשיעי ולאחד עשר
עשירי ששלשתן מקודשין, iy attem modim she-ilu kara le-tishi asiri u-le-asiri tishi
u-le-achad asar asiri she-sheloshtan mekudashin, don't you concede that when you call
nine and ten and eleven all ten that they're all that they're
all that they're all
sanctified? ואשתיקו בית הלל, Ve-ishteku Beis Hillel, and בית הלל Beis Hillel
didn't respond. Now תוספות Tosafot points out, of course they responded, they
responded in the משנה. Mishnah. They said this isn't an issue of
טעות, ta'os, it's an issue of the Torah designates that these are
also מעשר. ma'aser. But the point is that fine, but they a
little bit responded
by saying it's not based on טעות, ta'os, it's based on something
else. But they didn't directly respond within a טעות ta'os world. He
says they could have responded even within a טעות ta'os context. How
could they have responded within a טעות ta'os context? He says לימרו
להו, leimru la-ho, why didn't בית הלל Beis Hillel Why didn't they
say back to them, מה למעשר שכן אינו קדוש בכוונה? mah l'ma'aser
shekein einu kadosh bekavana? No, no, no, no, no.
מעשר, ma'aser, the reason תוס' Tos according to you, the reason תוס'
Tos works by מעשר, ma'aser, rather than saying it's based on something
other than תוס'. Tos. Why didn't they say, it is based on
תוס', Tos, maybe you're right, but the reason we have a principle
here of הקדש טעות hekdesh ta'us is because even because if you
tried intentionally right to sanctify it, you would not have succeeded if
you intentionally tried to do it, so how would this have explained
why it works
בטעות? b'ta'us?
Why would that have made it more explainable why it works? Here
it works בטעות b'ta'us
שכן אינו קדוש בכוונה. shekein einu kadosh bekavana. I mean that in
a way, I mean what I'm thinking about is really what the
גמרא's Gemara about to say, that it really then basically feeds into
the answer that בית הלל Beis Hillel actually did give בית שמאי.
Beis Shammai. But that somehow to say that this is an exception,
that since here you can't sanctify it even if you try to
sanctify it, right, normally a case of a טעות ta'us is we
all agree that it works בכוונה bekavana if you intentionally sanctify something,
and בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai says and
even if you accidentally sanctify something it'll also work, that's a case
of טעות, ta'us, right? So here, why didn't בית הלל Beis Hillel
say, hey buddy, this is like something this is obviously something completely
different going on here, right? The reason here, because here if you
intentionally try to make eleven into ten it doesn't work. It only
works eleven only becomes ten if you accidentally made a ten. So
clearly there's a different mechanism going on here and it's not just
a type of a of a הקדש טעות, hekdesh ta'us, okay? So
why didn't they say that? So the גמרא Gemara so according to
you that it didn't work בכוונה bekavana בית הלל Beis Hillel should
have pointed that out that it doesn't work בכוונה bekavana so clearly
there's a different mechanism. So אמר רב שימי בר אשי amar Rav
Shimi bar Ashi היינו טעמא דלא אמרי להו. hainu ta'ama delo amri
lehu.
Here's why בית הלל Beis Hillel did not say to בית שמאי
Beis Shammai hey, there's you know, it doesn't work בכוונה bekavana here
so clearly there's some other mechanism going on. דקל וחומר de-kal vachomer
because then בית שמאי Beis Shammai would have said back to בית
הלל Beis Hillel if anything that more proofs our point that טעות
ta'us should be a principle. מה מעשר שאינו קדוש בכוונה mah ma'aser
she'einu kadosh bekavana by מעשר ma'aser you can't intentionally sanctify eleven into
ten קדוש בטעות kadosh b'ta'us and טעות ta'us is still so powerful
that it makes it קדוש, kadosh, הקדש דקדוש בכוונה hekdesh d'kadosh bekavana
when you can intentionally sanctify something לא כל שכן lo kol shekein
certainly טעות ta'us should be effective. Okay, so here's the question: the
fact that מעשר ma'aser doesn't work בכוונה bekavana when you try to
make eleven ten, does that prove that the idea of טעות ta'us
is some completely separate principle, you can't prove to me anything about
טעות ta'us by מעשר ma'aser because clearly this is some weird idea
because it doesn't even work בכוונה? bekavana? So if it's working בטעות
b'ta'us that proves that something else is going on here. Or do
you say no, it proves how powerful טעות ta'us is, even in
a place where you can't be מקדיש makdish something בכוונה bekavana you
could be מקדיש makdish it בטעות. b'ta'us. So you see that טעות
ta'us is so powerful, טעות ta'us should always be a principle. Okay,
the obvious response is no, give me a break, that proves that
it's a different mechanism which is now what the גמרא Gemara says
right back. So it says ולא היא. v'lo hi. But that type
of a response, though let's make a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, look
how powerful טעות ta'us is, would not have been a legitimate response
of בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Why? דהקדש בדעתא דמרי תליא. d'hekdesh beda'ata
d'mari talya. Because in a normal הקדש hekdesh it's exactly that's the
exact point. If you need כוונה kavana and if כוונה kavana you
know, and if כוונה kavana in a place where כוונה kavana works,
that shows that you're the one that's making the הקדש hekdesh because
it's your כוונה kavana that works, okay? And if you have כוונה
kavana it does work, that shows it's all based on what you're
trying to do. So in that type of a case, in a
normal world of הקדש hekdesh where it goes by your כוונה, kavana,
we would say that if you made an error, that wasn't what
you were trying to do, and it wouldn't be binding. Here, the
fact that it doesn't work when you try to make eleven ten
shows that the point is not that הקדש hekdesh is defined by
what you're trying to do, הקדש hekdesh is defined here by something
else. מעשר ma'aser is defined not by what you're trying to do,
but by something else, right? So therefore it's a different mechanism that's
operating here. Here, what's making it מעשר ma'aser is the fact that
it was called ten. Either it was called ten because it was
ten, or it was called ten with an honest mistake and that
allows it to be considered a legitimate calling of ten. Okay, but
if you intentionally called eleven ten, that's not a calling of ten,
that's a mislabeling, that's a conscious mislabeling. Okay, but the point here
is is that so yeah, if he
called eight ten, it also doesn't work.
It has to be within a certain range and it has to
be an honest mistake and so on, which proves that it's a
different mechanism, which is exactly what בית הלל Beis Hillel said back
to בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. This isn't a normal mechanism of הקדש.
hekdesh. This is a mechanism that's not אשבחת ashbachat but אטעות at'us
and it's about being called ten. So basically the point is like
this, one more time because I think it's a little confusing, which
is, if this only works בטעות b'ta'us and not בכוונה, bekavana, then
why didn't בית הלל Beis Hillel say back to בית שמאי, Beis
Shammai, look, I'll prove to you there's a different mechanism going on
here, because it only works בטעות b'ta'us it doesn't work בכוונה. bekavana.
That was the question. And the answer
is
that... of a point is no, that proves that it's a different
mechanism. If it's not working בכוונה, be-kavanah, that shows that it's not
normal הקדש. hekdesh. It's not based on what you're trying to do.
When it's based on what you're trying to do and what your
דעת da'as is, then טעות ta'ut would not be your דעת da'as
and טעות ta'ut would not work. The reason טעות ta'ut works here
is דוקא davka because you're because it's based on a completely different
mechanism, on what was called 10, you know, with an honest type
of a mistake and within a reasonable range. That's defined as מעשר,
ma'aser, not on what you're intentionally trying to do. Is that clear?
Did I succeed in losing everybody? Yes, Jenna.
That's fair, but I think I'm still confused about the setup of
the משנה. mishnah. Are they arguing, do they agree on our original
statement in the משנה mishnah and thus are using that agreement exactly
as a דוקא davka argument that they have? Exactly. Right. Everybody agrees
that a נזיר nazir who retroactively isn't a נזיר, nazir, the animal
isn't קדוש. kadosh. So בית הלל Beis Hillel tries to say, you
see הקדש hekdesh doesn't work, and the implicit answer is that's not
just טעות, ta'ut, that's fundamentally your message, and everybody agrees retroactively that
a everybody agrees that a מעשר ma'aser that 9 and 11 count
as 10. So בית שמאי Beis Shamai says you see that that's
evidence that טעות ta'ut works. And בית הלל Beis Hillel says that's
not based on טעות, ta'ut, that's based on a different type of
a mechanism. Okay, so it got a little confusing here about this
debate about what would be if it was intentional, but the basic
point is the reason בית הלל Beis Hillel doesn't bring up the
issue of that בכוונה be-kavanah doesn't matter is because בית שמאי Beis
Shamai could have turned it into a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. But
bottom line is, whatever קל וחומר kal va-chomer בית שמאי Beis Shamai
would have turned it into, the real logic is that the fact
that it only works בטעות be-ta'ut and not בכוונה be-kavanah even more
proves that it's a completely different mechanism. Fundamental הקדש hekdesh works בכוונה,
be-kavanah, and that's why טעות ta'ut is not going to be an
issue is not going to be הקדש. hekdesh. This דוקא davka works
בטעות be-ta'ut and not בכוונה be-kavanah because it's a completely different mechanism
of why the thing becomes מעשר, ma'aser, not because of the principle
of טעות, ta'ut, but because of a question of what was designated
as the tenth. Okay, now we go on to the next משנה.
mishnah. Okay, which gets us back actually to נזירות בטעות. neziros be-ta'ut.
So let's take a
look. מי שנדר בנזיר והלך להביא את בהמתו, Mi she-nadar be-nazir ve-halach
le-havi es behemto, somebody made a נדר neder as a נזיר nazir
and he went to get his animal. מצאה שנגנבה, Matza she-nigneva, and
he found that the animal had been stolen. And this is a
guy that basically is going to a חכם chacham and saying, "I'm
a poor guy, I can only afford, you know, I didn't have
the money to buy extra animals, I only would have been a
נזיר nazir had I had that animal available, and now it turns
out that it was stolen. Had I known that, I never would
have been a נזיר." nazir. So what's the הלכה? halachah? אם עד
שלא נגנבה בהמתו נדר, Im ad she-lo nigneva behemto nadar, if he
took his נזירות neziros before his animal was stolen, הרי זה נזיר.
harei zeh nazir. Then he's a נזיר nazir because then at the
time you took your נזירות, neziros, you were intending to be a
נזיר nazir even had your animal was around. Okay? The fact that
it got stolen later, that couldn't have been
anticipated. ואם משנגנבה בהמתו נדר, Ve-im mi-she-nigneva behemto nadar, but if it
was stolen
already at the time you took your נזירות neziros it had stolen,
you weren't aware of it but it happened to have been stolen,
אינו נזיר. eino nazir. Then it's not. So that's a type of
a טעות, ta'ut, right? But it works through the process of going
to a חכם chacham and getting a היתר heter and saying, "Had
you realized when you took your נזירות neziros that your animal had
already been stolen, would you have accepted the נזירות?" neziros? And you
say no. So then he gives you a היתר. heter. Ah, so
we see it was actually done בטעות, be-ta'ut, in error, okay? That's
a classic case about a היתר heter of a חכם, chacham, okay?
And you're free from now this basically is the position of בית
הלל Beis Hillel because בית שמאי Beis Shamai doesn't really accept the
idea of נזירות בטעות. neziros be-ta'ut. And the whole idea of a
היתר חכם heter chacham is fundamentally based on the idea of טעות,
ta'ut, because had you known at that time now you couldn't have
said, "Had I known at the time in the future it would
have been stolen." That was nothing you could have known at that
time, so we can't use what happened after your נזירות neziros to
retroactively define your frame of mind as to having been in error.
Okay, so that's a principle called אין פותחין בנולד. ein potchin be-nolad.
You don't open up the door for somebody about something that was
going to be have given birth to later, meaning something that was
not it was not a fact at the time the vow was
taken, only would have been in the future. However, if it is
something that somebody could have anticipated, right? Then you can be פותח
בנולד. poteach be-nolad. And this was a whole discussion we had in
נדרים, Nedarim, right? So if it was like a case where somebody
said like, "Had you been aware, you know, if it was like
a young a young kid, had you been aware that your parents
would have been upset when they found out you took this נדר,
neder, would you have taken it?" And he said, "No, had I
realized they would have been upset." Well, if it could have been
anticipated that they would have been upset when they would have found
out, so even though they weren't upset yet, right? But had but
it's something that you could say, "Had you thought through this and
realized that very likely they would have been upset, you know, and
would you have then gone and done it?" "No, had I thought
about that and thought that that was likely or whatever, I wouldn't
have." Right? So that's a case about פותחין בנולד, potchin be-nolad, but
it's a נולד nolad that's that you can anticipate. The idea that
it would have gotten stolen is not something that could be anticipated.
So if it hadn't been stolen yet and wasn't... something he reasonably
could have been anticipated, then, you know, we're not fortune tellers. You
can't retroactively say, "Had I known the future, I wouldn't have taken
the vow." There's no way you could have known the future. Yes.
Oh, I was talking about the התרה. Hatara.
You're right, it's not said explicitly. I mean, it's based on what
we know from הלכות נדרים. Hilchos Nedarim. I mean, it's not explicit
here in this, in this... Right, I mean, putting it here, well,
no, if anything, putting it here you could have said maybe it's
based on a תוספות Tosfos without even the need of התרה. Hatara.
Right, maybe the previous משנה Mishnah was והשילו, Vihishilo, ונשילו, Vineshilo, right.
That's true, that's true. Look, it's really based on what we know
from מסכת נדרים, Maseches Nedarim, you know, that when you make it
based on some sort of some type of a
unexplicated assumption, there are cases where if you explicate your assumption, you
know, that we could say you don't even need a התרה, Hatara,
right? Like you say, "Oh, since I have so many animals, I'm
prepared to accept and use," whatever. So that might be a case,
you know, but it is, but what we know from מסכת נדרים
Maseches Nedarim is that when it's based on an unexplicated assumption, you
have to, you need a process of התרה. Hatara. But you're right,
it's not explicit here. We're reading in other things that we're assuming.
Okay. So, now, וזו טעות, Vezu Ta'us, this error, it's interesting because
the whole thing is based on טעות, Ta'us, right? נזירות בטעות, Nezirous
B'ta'us, הקדש בטעות, Hekdesh B'ta'us, but now we're going to say an
error in law. Okay, the following error טעה נחום המדי. Ta'ah Nachum
HaMadai. נחום המדי Nachum HaMadai made it. So he made a different
type of a טעות, Ta'us, not a הקדש בטעות Hekdesh B'ta'us or
נזירות בטעות, Nezirous B'ta'us, but a פסק טעות. Psak Ta'us. כשעלו נזירים
מן הגולה, Keshe'alu Nezirim Min HaGolah, and
נזירים Nezirim came from exile to bring their קרבנות ירושלים, Korbanos Yerushalayim,
ומצאו בית המקדש חרב, U'matzu Beis HaMikdash Charev, and they found the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed. It's such a fascinating משנה, Mishnah,
right, a little historical insight. People were נזירים Nezirim out in the
exile, they hadn't heard that the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed,
and they came with their קרבנות. Korbanos. אמר להם נחום המדי, Amar
Lahem Nachum HaMadai, נחום המדי Nachum HaMadai said to them, "אילו הייתם
יודעים שבית המקדש חרב הייתם נוזרים? Illu Heyissem Yodim SheBeis HaMikdash Charev
Hayissem Nozerim? Had you known that the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash would
have been destroyed when you accepted your נזירות, Nezirous, would you have
become נזירים?" Nezirim? אמרו לו לא, Amru Lo Lo, they said no.
והתירה נחום המדי, Ve'hitira Nachum HaMadai, and he permitted it to them.
Now, that was an error because when they accepted their נזירות, Nezirous,
it had not been destroyed. Okay, maybe they were out living in
the mountains or something, you know, like a good hermit or something.
So anyway, they didn't hear, but presumably they had accepted their נזירות
Nezirous when it was still around. And he said, "Had you known
it would have been destroyed?" So that was about something that was
had not yet existed and he was using that as the basis
for a היתר. Heter. וכשבא דבר אצל חכמים אמרו, U'keshe'ba Davar Etzel
Chachamim Amru, when it came to the sages they said, "כל שנזר
עד שלא חרב בית המקדש נזיר ומשחרב בית המקדש אינו נזיר." Kol
She'nazar Ad Shelo Charav Beis HaMikdash Nazir, U'meshecharav Beis HaMikdash Eino Nazir.
Nope. If you accepted it before the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is
destroyed, then you're still a נזיר. Nazir. The fact, how are you
supposed to know the future? If you accepted it after it was
destroyed and you hadn't yet heard that it was destroyed, then you're
not a נזיר, Nazir, because then that was something that was, you
know, that had you known already at that time it was destroyed,
it was an important piece of fact that you were
unaware of, and had you been aware of it, you wouldn't have
made it. That's a טעות. Ta'us. But what would have happened in
the future, you know, that's not something that you were in error
about. You don't know the future. Yes, so.
Didn't we have a משנה Mishnah a while back that said that
or we discussed that someone who makes a נזיר נדר Nazir Neder
outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael has to come to ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael to observe it? So he wouldn't have been able to
start it yet.
No, no, no, they just have to do it again in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and that's only a דרבנן. Derabbanan. Yes, a bunch
of דרבנן. Derabbanan. Yeah, yeah,
but that's a good point also, which is what if somebody says,
"I'll be a נזיר Nazir after thirty days," and between now and
thirty days something new occurs that makes him not want to be
it? How much presumably the facts that feed into the idea of
חרטה Charata have to be at the time the נדר Neder was
made, not the נדר Neder takes effect.
Okay, that's not
just a נזיר, Nazir, it's, right, that's in general for a נדר.
Neder. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבה,
Amar Rabba, שטפלו רבנן לרבי אליעזר, Shetfulu Rabbanan l'Rabbi Eliezer, the Rabbis
flooded רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, meaning they overwhelmed him, ואוקמוה בשיטתייהו, V'okmu
b'shitasaihu, and they basically got him to agree to them. Because רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was around at the time of the חורבן הבית,
Churban Habayis, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer actually says that you are
allowed to be פותחין בנולד, potechin b'nolad, you're actually allowed to say,
"Had you realized what would have happened in the future," and that
that actually is a basis for being מתיר matir a נדר Neder
and מתיר matir a נזירות. Nezirous. But nevertheless, when the Rabbis here
overruled נחום המדי, Nachum HaMadai, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is silent, right?
רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer voice isn't being recorded in this משנה. Mishnah.
So presumably they basically, you know, they either convinced him or silenced
him, one or the other, but they overwhelmed his position. And now,
what is this? Because he didn't say, "One minute, I think what
רב נחום המדי Rav Nachum HaMadai did was okay." No, he was
silent. And what's this רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? דתנן: Ditnan: פותחין בנולד,
Potechin B'nolad, דברי רבי אליעזר. Divrei Rabbi Eliezer. You can open up
the door for somebody about something, you can, you know, make it
to say, "Hey, had you realized X and Y and Z would
have happened after your vow, would you have taken your vow?" And
the person says, "No." And then, "Okay, so fine, you're released," even
based on something that happened after the vow was taken. וחכמים אוסרין,
Ve'Chachamim Ossrin, and the חכמים Chachamim forbid it. Okay, so you see
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer did not come to back up נחום המדי,
Nachum HaMadai, so the חכמים Chachamim overwhelmed him. Now, ואמר רבא, Ve'Amar
Rava, עד לא גב דאמרי רבנן, Ad lo gav damar Rabbanan, even
though the Rabbis say you can't be פותחין בנולד... potechin b'nolad... אבל
פותחין בתנאי נולד. aval potchin b'tnai nolad. You can open up with
a condition of a נולד. nolad. What does that mean? היכי דמי?
heichi dami? What's the case? אמי להון, ami lehon, you say to
them, אילו אתא איניש ואמי לכון דחרב בית המקדש מי הוית נדריתא?
ilu ata inish ve'ami l'chon de'charav Beis HaMikdash mi haveisa nadrisah? Had
people come and said to you, you could have said to the
נזירים nezirim the following thing: not had you known the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash would have been destroyed because that's נולד, nolad, but had
people come to you and said to you that hey buddy, the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash might be destroyed any day now, had they
said that to you, would you have still taken your נזירות? neziros?
So that he says that's okay, and if the guy says no,
then you can מתיר. matir. Now what makes that case different? Okay,
so my initial response to this is it's similar to sort of
say a נולד השכיח. nolad ha'shkiach. Basically it means if people would
have said this to you, meaning had somebody said to you, hey,
the Romans are surrounding the city, the political, a lot of political
unrest, had you stopped to realize that it was a reasonable possibility,
would you have done it?
And they say, you know what? Right, I was ignoring all the
signs, I wasn't reading the newspaper or whatever, I was just convinced
that God was going to save us, but had I stopped to
really take an honest assessment, I probably wouldn't have done it, right?
So then it's not just a who, I don't have a future
ball, it's no, had I really thought about that it was a
likely possibility I wouldn't have done it.
So that's of a נולד השכיח. nolad ha'shkiach. Okay, so that's how
I would have read it. But תוספות Tosfos reads this differently. תוספות
Tosfos emphasizes that fact
that people would
have said it to you, which means that it's really not so
much about whether the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash would or wouldn't have
been destroyed, but had people basically tried to convince you
not to do it, would you have
listened to them?
Because we tend to listen to people who are pressuring us to
do things whether or not that's what we really want to be
doing or not. So if all your family was yelling at you
and telling you, you're stupid, the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is going
to be destroyed, you won't be able to bring a קרבן, korban,
this and that, would you have done it anyway? Not because you
were worried that the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash would be destroyed, but
would you have done it anyway in defiance of the pressure that
you were getting from your family? And if the person says, oh
no, then I wouldn't have done it, so then we could say,
oh okay. Now it's a little funny though, because he didn't actually
get that pressure, right? The people didn't actually say that to him.
So it's a little bit strange that had you been tried to,
had your friends tried to persuade you, would you have done it?
And he says no, I wouldn't have done it had they tried
to persuade me. Why does that matter? They didn't try to persuade
him. So I don't understand why that really matters so much. Yeah,
perhaps they're trying to make the point that he didn't understand the
personal implications. It's not just a political geo-physical process, it's he was
then all alone. Yeah, but again, I agree, but then that's not
if people would have tried to persuade you, then it's just like
had you realized that there was a reasonable likelihood this would have
happened and you would have been a נזיר עולם, nazir olam, would
you have done it? That's how I would read this. That's not
about the idea of the friends persuading, right? If the friends actually
tried to persuade you, yeah, so I mean if you want to
see, here the רא"ש Rosh says the following, he says, the רא"ש
Rosh says, where's the רא"ש? Rosh? אבל פותחין בתנאי נולד, aval potchin
b'tnai nolad, it's about eight lines down from the תוספות Tosfos where
it says שישה. shisha. The רא"ש Rosh says the following: דאמינא להו
אילו אתו אינשי דאמרי לכו דחרב בית המקדש מי הוית נדריתא? אילו
היו באים אנשים והיו נותנים לכם עצה שלא תדרו אולי יחרב בית
המקדש טרם כלות נזירותכם, כלום הייתם נוזרים? ואמרו כן היינו נמלחים ושומעים
לעצתם. de'amina lehu ilu asu inshi de'omri l'chu de'charav Beis HaMikdash mi
haveisa nadrisah? Ilu hayu baim anashim v'hayu nosnim lachem eitzah she'lo tidru
ulai yecharav Beis HaMikdash terem klos neziroschem, klum hayitem nozrim? V'omru ken
hayinu nimlachim v'shomim l'atzasam. You know what? If they had advised us,
then we would have listened to their advice. פתח הוי אף על
פי שהעצה תלויה בנולד דדמי להו דדמי לאדם הנמלך על דעת הנודרים,
אילו באו עשרה בני אדם ופייסוך שלא היית נודר כלום היית נודר?
דהוי פתח. הכא נמי כיון שתולה חרטתו בעצת אנשים פתח הוי, אף
על פי שהעצה היתה מחמת דבר הנולד לא קרינן ביה נולד, כיון
שמחמת עצתם היה חוזר. Pesach havei af al pi she'haeitzah tluyah b'nolad
d'dami lehu d'dami l'adam hanimlach al daas hanodrim, ilu bau asarah bnei
adam v'piysucha she'lo hayisa noder klum hayisa noder? D'havei pesach. Hecha nami
kivan she'toleh charataso b'atzas anashim pesach havei, af al pi she'haeitzah haysa
machmas davar hanolad lo karinan bei nolad, kivan she'machmas atzasam hayah chozer.
If people had advised me otherwise, I would have listened to their
advice. Okay, but I still don't get it because they didn't advise
him. So maybe it's still just a way of saying like had
you really stopped to take stock, like had you really, had somebody
whose judgment you trust told you that this was not a good
idea, right? So now retroactively it's like so imagine that you're incorporating
good judgment now going back to the time you took the vow,
had you been making good judgment and really thought the issue through.
But again, to me it's easier to see this as a way
of saying like had you been thinking about this and had you
been making a good type of decisions and good judgment or advised
properly but ultimately taking the advice not because of the pressure but
because that was like the right type of judgment to be made,
yeah. Two thoughts. First of all, I have to spend some time
processing this in light of contemporary political arguments and polemics. Right, exactly.
But it's also interesting that this unusual phrase where שפו רבנן מרבי
אליעזר, Shafu Rabbanan meRabbi Eliezer, that's what we're talking about, right? They're
so overwhelm— Oh, that's a nice point! Yeah, that he couldn't respond.
Right, right, that's a good point because it sort of seems like
not that they really persuaded him, but it was just like they
were pre— he was pressured by the overwhelming consensus. That's a nice,
that's a very nice point. So let's take a look. Anyway, so
that's the צנין ולובא. Tzinan u-Lava. Somehow either it means had you
like, you know, really thought through the possibility and been— and been
sort of the beneficiary of good advice, would you have done that?
And— or somehow also because had people pressured you, maybe that somehow
becomes a way of a פתח. petach. But I don't get the
pressure, I— I sort of get the advice idea. Anyway, let's take
a look. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, says Rav Yosef, אי
הואי התם, ei havai hatam, if I were there, הוי אמינא, hava
amina, I would say להון, lehon, הכתיב, ha-ketiv, I would have gotten
the נזירים nezirim off by the following way. I would have said,
היכל ה' היכל ה' היכל ה' המה. Heichal Hashem Heichal Hashem Heichal
Hashem heima. So basically, this is the פסוק pasuk from ירמיהו Yirmiyahu
where the people are saying, oh, the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash isn't
going to be destroyed, it's God's היכל. Heichal. God is not going
to protect it. מקדש ראשון ומקדש שני. Mikdash rishon u-Mikdash sheni. So
that's— oh, God didn't destroy the first— you know, God— it's so—
actually, this is— this is like, you know, well, the time of
ירמיהו Yirmiyahu is the first בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But anyway, you
know, there'll be a first בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, second בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, God will always protect it. So— so— yeah, I know
it's a little bit funny. So anyway, נהי דידעיתון להו דיחרב. nehi
de-yadeitun lehu de-yicharav. Okay, so anyway, I mean basically, he would have
said, look, here the people were saying it won't be destroyed and
ירמיהו Yirmiyahu is telling them that you're trusting in this false faith,
it is going to be destroyed, okay? And therefore what he would
have said to them is look, you know, you knew ultimately, you
know, this was from the second בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the
פסוק pasuk going back to ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. So it seems like he
basically would have said to them like look, you know in the
time of ירמיהו Yirmiyahu already people thought that it wasn't going to
be destroyed and it was, and the פסוק pasuk already sort of
prophesies implicitly, not that the people knew that it was a second
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash as תוספות Tosafot points out, then they would
have thought the first one wouldn't be destroyed, but the פסוק pasuk
is implicitly telling you that there will be one בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, second בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, that the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
will be destroyed even when people think it won't. So had you
sort of realized that, you know, had you realized that ultimately it's—
you know, God— this— this has happened before in history and that
God is basically telling us that the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is
going to be destroyed, you know, you should have realized that that
was going to happen. So it was sort of like a נולד
השכיח, nolad hashachiach, like it should have been something you should have
anticipated that was going to happen. And had you thought that through,
would you still have taken your נדר? neder? So the גמרא Gemara
says— what's the גמרא's Gemara response? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, I'm sorry,
נהי דידעיתון להו דיחרב מי ידעיתון לאימת. nehi de-yadeitun lehu de-yicharav mi
yadeitun le-eimas. No, no, no, no. That would not have been a
good way out. Because even if they would have said look, you
know, you're right, had we stopped to sort of think— take stock,
we might have realized that eventually the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash would
be destroyed, but, you know, who says that we would have realized
it was going to happen before we were done with our נזירות?
nezirus? Like there was no reason for that to, you know, have
gotten us to not accept the נזירות nezirus even though we might
be— eventually it would be destroyed. One minute. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
ולא ידעיתון לאימת? ve-lo yadeitun le-eimas? How could they not know? והא
כתיב שבעים שבעים נחתך על עמך ועל עיר קדשך. ve-ha ketiv shavuim
shivim nechtach al amcha ve-al ir kodshecha. Seventy sevens or whatever, you
know, that after four hundred and ninety years— this is a פסוק
pasuk in דניאל Daniel from— I don't know, the destruction of the
first בית המקדש— Beis Hamikdash is the way חז"ל Chazal read it,
the second one will be destroyed. So you should have realized! You
know, if you would have read the פסוקים, pesukim, if you would
have been a little bit more realistic or
whatever, you should have realized it would have been destroyed.
So I would have gotten them off the hook that way. So
the גמרא Gemara is not happy with this. The גמרא Gemara says
ואכתי מי ידענא בהאי יומא?
ve-achti
mi yadeina be-hai yoma?
No, no, no. They still didn't know like exactly when. All right,
roughly. Exactly, not in the next thirty days. But it is interesting,
right? Because I mean you think about it like given the political
realities, you know, and but also you read about the history of
the time, you know, the people were blind to the— you know,
they were persuaded that they were going to hold off Rome forever,
right? That, you know, God would protect them and they would hold
off Rome and they've initially been quite successful against the largest army
of the world, so, you know. So exactly. And so היכל ה'
Heichal Hashem comes— so the גמרא Gemara is that this is not—
but this is a human mindset. I mean I know plenty of
people today who are convinced— that they know there was a destruction
of the first temple and the second. But they believe that, you
know, that— that now is our time and everything's going in a
positive direction and nothing can happen. Right, right, exactly.
Right, right, right.
Except if we're talking about Iran.
Right, exactly.
So I think that's what— exactly— I think that's exactly true. I
think that's how the ראש Rosh reads it, which is like that,
you know— let's take a look at the ראש. Rosh. He says—
he
says, ומפרש ליה רבותינו, u-mefarash lei raboseinu, that's twelve lines before the
lines get wide, סוף ומפרש
ליה רבותינו, sof u-mefarash lei raboseinu, שהיו מוכיח את הרשעים, she-hayu mochiach
es ha-reshaim, ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, שהיו מתייאשים מן הפורענות. she-hayu misyaashim min ha-puranus.
ואמרי אם יחרב היכל ה' עוד יבנה לנו היכל בית שני, אם
יחרב גם אותו עוד יבנה לנו שלישי לימות המשיח. ve-amri im yeicharev
Heichal Hashem od yibaneh lanu Heichal bayis sheni, im yeicharev gam oso
od yibaneh lanu shelishi liyemos ha-Mashiach. So anyway, you know, they'll be...
duping yourselves, right? The same way they duped themselves in the time
of ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. That's how he tries to get them to realize
it was a טעות. toas. No? I mean but I hear your
point. Your point is what? That they wouldn't have conceded that it
was a טעות? toas? Now they're trying to get out of their
נזירות. nezirus. Now it's already destroyed. There's no reason for them...
the גמרא Gemara says of היכל השם Heichal Hashem regarding the בית
המקדש השני. Beis HaMikdash HaSheini. Aha.
That the
ירמיהו's Yirmiyahu warning and the people's refusal to listen to him is
always, you know, is always operating. Right, just the fact that he
was right once doesn't convince anyone.
I see. I see. That's a good point. Right. Okay, yeah. טוב.
Tov. Right, right, right. Yeah, then right, then they were duped. Now
we're now we know, like, it's not going to happen, right.
At this point... it's real clear that ירמיהו Yirmiyahu is prophesying the
destruction of the first temple. Right. It's really not clear that he's
talking about the second. No kidding. And the second thing is this
talk about the four hundred ninety years. That's not obvious from the
פסוקים. pesukim. And even more so, these are אמוראים Amoraim talking about
a derivation from סדר עולם Seder Olam which hadn't been written yet.
Right. And the whole counting wasn't... so I mean it reinforces דב'ס
Dov's point, which is like, it's very nice in hindsight to say,
'Oh look, it was quite clear it was going to be a
second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash it was going to be destroyed, it
was going to be four hundred ninety years.' For the people living
at that time, as דב Dov was like... 'That was the first
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's not going to happen again.' Like, this
פסוק posuk in דניאל Daniel means something else, or whatever. Right? If
you're in hindsight, it's all very clear what these פסוקים pesukim might
might be read to mean. For those living at that time, it
wasn't. But you know, but that was after the חורבן הבית, Churban
HaBayis, so maybe they would be persuaded like, 'Don't you want to
see how this was really in hindsight obvious and you should have
realized this at the time?' But you're right, like...
yeah.
Is it possible that that אגדתא agaddata of... I mean that that
sense of, 'Oh, it's ten people had told you,' or whatever, that
it's saying the mistake was on the part of the people, like
everyone? That like, no one was warning you, like, you should have
all known and like we all made the mistake of thinking... Aha.
Yeah, but if that's true, then I understand... then it's harder to
argue why that should get you out of your vow, right?
Because it was like a communal mistake. Right. That probably doesn't...
Yeah, but I'm not sure how... I understand your point, but I'm
not sure how like if we were all in a sense duped,
why that means that it was like...
because what we have to get to is not the objective facts,
like, we have to get to the mind... I guess what you're
saying is like
had we all been able to like take a step back, we
all would have realized the following thing. Like, we were all sort
of... I get why you couldn't weren't able to sort of think
about it at that time, but that was because we were all
sort of being like, you know, persuaded a certain way. Maybe that's
an interesting way of thinking about it. Okay, very fascinating, but yeah.
It's interesting to see at what point that transition takes place. Right.
In other words, you're not... you know, if you have faith in
something... Right. So you think up until the last minute, we have
to have strong faith. And then at some point...
Yeah. And it doesn't always right, and things don't shift, it's true
also, they don't shift immediately the day after, right, you know, it's
true, like you still cling on to that and no, no, no,
it's something's going to... right? I understand. Like, so even the ability
to say, 'Hey, I'm going to help you get out of your
נזירות nezirus if you could just concede to the point that you
were sort of like, you know, completely being, you know, had a
false faith before.' It's like you're not ready maybe to concede to
that point, right? I totally agree. Yeah, and I think you know,
דב'ס Dov's point also, like, you know, just because it happened before,
even if it just happened a week ago, doesn't mean I'm wrong,
or doesn't mean... right, you know, you're still holding on to that
faith. Let's just read this משנה, Mishnah, finish the דף. daf.
היו מהלכין בדרך... Hayu mehalchin baderech... so you
and
some have the גרסא girsa ששה, shisha, six people were going on
the way. ואחד בא כנגדן veechad ba kinegedan and one guy was
coming to this up to this group. ואמר אחד מהן vamar echad
meihen and one of this group said, 'Oh, I know that, that's
ראובן.' Reuven.
הריני נזיר שזה פלוני, Hareini nazir shezeh ploni, 'I'll be a I'll
be a נזיר nazir if that's ראובן Reuven coming to us.' ואחד
אמר, veechad amar, הריני נזיר שאין זה פלוני, Hareini nazir she-ein zeh
ploni, 'Ah you're crazy, that's not ראובן. Reuven. I'll be a נזיר
nazir if it isn't ראובן.' Reuven. Okay. הריני נזיר, Hareini nazir, then
number three says, הריני נזיר שאחד מכם נזיר, Hareini nazir she-echad mikem
nazir, 'I'll be a נזיר nazir if one of you are a
נזיר.' nazir. And one of them has got to be a נזיר,
nazir, either way, either it is ראובן Reuven or it isn't ראובן.
Reuven. So guy number
three thinks seems like he'd definitely have to be a נזיר. nazir.
Okay. Now the guy number four says, שאין אחד מכם נזיר, she-ein
echad mikem nazir, 'I'll be a נזיר nazir if one of you
is not a נזיר.' nazir. Now also one of them is not,
right? It's like the old joke, I have two coins in my
hand that equal thirty-five cents, one of them is not a quarter,
what are they? And the answer is a quarter and a dime,
because one of them is not a quarter. All right anyway, so
anyway, so the guy said, 'I'm a נזיר nazir if one of
you isn't a נזיר,' nazir, one of them isn't a נזיר, nazir,
okay, even if the other one is.
Sounds like no one is a נזיר. nazir. Yeah, I know, that's
a good point. Okay, but ששניכם נזירים. sheshneichem nezirim. Now,
number five says I'll be a נזיר nazir if the first two
of you are נזירים, nezirim, which does not seem like that's going
to work, because the first two of them are not נזירים. nezirim.
Maybe he means numbers three and four are נזירים, nezirim, then it
should work. And then number six says שכולכם נזירים, shekulchem nezirim, I'm
a נזיר nazir if all of you are נזירים, nezirim, which would
seem like that can't be true, they're not all נזירים. nezirim. Okay,
anyway, בית שמאי אומרים כולם נזירים. Beit Shammai omrim kulam nezirim.
So how did that happen? So basically, this is בית שמאי's Beit
Shammai position, that a נזיר בטעות nazir beta'ut is a נזיר, nazir,
okay, and it's considered to be a טעות ta'ut because everybody thinks
what they're saying is correct, right? Everybody's no, he's not ראובן Reuven
and I'm going to I'll be a נזיר nazir to prove that
he's not, meaning it's not that they everybody everyone wants to be
a נזיר nazir here. They just they're just mistaken what they think
but whether they think they're you know some people are right, some
people are wrong in terms of what they believe is the situation,
but everybody wants to be a נזיר, nazir, so therefore they're all
נזירים, nezirim, you know, and if your condition wasn't met, that was
an error on your part but you wanted to be a נזיר.
nazir. Okay,
בית הלל אומרים אינו נזיר אלא מי שלא נתקיימו דבריו. Beit Hillel
omrim eino nazir ela mi shelo nitkaymu devarav. The only person who
is a נזיר nazir is the one who was wrong. What? So
the גמרא Gemara immediately switches it to mean the one who was
right. Okay, so that's a very bizarre, okay, but anyway the גמרא
Gemara switches it to mean בית הלל Beit Hillel says the normal
thing. The people whose conditions were met are נזירים, nezirim, and the
people whose conditions are not met are not נזירים. nezirim. רבי טרפון
אומר אין אחד מהם נזיר. Rabbi Tarfon omer ein echad mehem nazir.
Nobody's a נזיר. nazir. He is the exact opposite of בית שמאי.
Beit Shammai. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says that לא ניתנה נזירות אלא
להפלאה, lo nitna nezirut ela lehafla'ah, כי יפלי לנדור נדר נזיר ki
yafli lindor neder nazir means articulate, which means it has to be
clear at the time the vow is taken that you're that you're
a נזיר. nazir. And therefore since there's a doubt who's a נזיר
nazir based on what the condition is met, okay, even if objectively
he is ראובן Reuven or he isn't from some omniscient point of
view it is it is clear, but since for them it's not
clear at the time that they're a נזיר, nazir, then it's not
binding. Now the problem should be that guys number three and four
should definitely be a נזיר, nazir, because the guy number three said
I'm a נזיר nazir if one of you is a נזיר, nazir,
right? Well, that was true, one of them was a נזיר, nazir,
that was going to be clear. Okay, but according to רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon no, because רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon would say one and
two are not נזירים nezirim because since their thing was in a
doubt, neither one or two, right, they made the condition, are נזירים.
nezirim. So therefore when three said I'm a נזיר nazir if one
of you is a נזיר, nazir, well, he wasn't a neither one
or two were a נזיר nazir according to רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon,
so three also isn't נזיר. nazir. How about four? Four said I'm
a נזיר nazir if one of you is not a נזיר. nazir.
Now that was true, because right, none of them were a נזיר.
nazir. So so the way תוספות Tosafot reads this is that number
four was saying I'm a נזיר nazir if one and only one
of you is not a נזיר, nazir, meaning one is not and
one is. That's a little not so clear, okay, but anyway so
according to רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon one and two are not a
נזיר nazir and therefore three and four are not a נזיר nazir
and therefore obviously five and six because five and six said everybody
is a נזיר. nazir. Okay, so that's רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. החזיר
פניו לאחוריו, Hechezir panav leachorav,
let's say the guy turned around and we never found out who
he was.
So and this is now within בית הלל Beit Hillel that says
you're a נזיר nazir if your condition is met. Right, if according
to בית שמאי Beit Shammai you're always a נזיר. nazir. According to
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon you're never a נזיר. nazir. בית הלל Beit
Hillel says you're a נזיר nazir if your condition is met. So
let's say the guy turned around, so what's the story? אינו נזיר.
eino nazir. So the הלכה halacha is if we can't figure out
if your condition is met, then you're not a נזיר, nazir, okay,
which is also interesting, right, why would that be? Why don't we
say you're a ספק נזיר? safek nazir? רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, oh
like turned and they all do this and they're like oh crap
what did we just do and they run the other way so
they never see who the guy is.
That would be a good way to solve it, that's a good
okay. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says the logical thing in this case that you're a ספק נזיר.
safek nazir. יאמר אם היה כדברי הריני נזיר חובה ואם לאו הריני
נזיר נדבה, Yomar im haya kidevarai hareni nazir chovah ve'im lav hareni
nazir nedavah, if my condition was met,
then I'm a נזיר nazir because of what I accepted upon myself,
and if not,
then I accept a free-will which you have to do because if
you're a ספק נזיר, safek nazir, how does your נזירות nezirut ever
end? You can't bring a קרבן korban because maybe you're not a
נזיר. nazir. So the only way a ספק נזיר safek nazir can
end his נזירות nezirut is by accepting a optional נזירות, nezirut, a
free-will נזירות nezirut upon himself, so on condition, either I'm a definite
נזיר nazir or if I'm not already a נזיר nazir I'm accepting
a נזירות nezirut now. And then one way or the other you're
a נזיר nazir and you bring a קרבן. korban. So what we
have is again the position of בית שמאי Beit Shammai that says
that if you wanted to become a נזיר nazir because you thought
your condition was being met, then whether it was met or wasn't
met you're a נזיר, nazir, that's נזירות בטעות. nezirut beta'ut. You have
the opposite extent extreme which is רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon who says
that לא ניתנה נזירות אלא להפלאה lo nitna nezirut ela lehafla'ah and
if your condition is not definitely met at the time that you're
accepting it, you're not a נזיר. nazir. And then you have the
reasonable middle position of בית הלל Beit Hillel which is it depends
on whether your condition is met. And then the second stage is
according to בית הלל Beit Hillel if there's a ספק safek if
your condition is met, what's the story? רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says
you're a ספק נזיר *safek nazir* and the first opinion says you're
ודאי *vadai* not a נזיר *nazir* if there's a doubt if it
was met and we'll have to figure that one out as well.
Let's take five more minutes.